<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="wp_calibrate__profile_unstable_v1">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2019 Erwin Burema

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="zwp_calibration_manager_v1" version="1">
      <description summary="Manager object for profiling/calibration of displays">
          With this interface a compositor can announce calibration/profiling
          support so a software can calibrate the display. This protocol should
          be priviliged.

          Currently this is just a sketch for a proposal

          THIS INTERFACE IS EXPERIMENTAL!
      </description>

      <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
        <description summary="destroy the calibration manager">
            Destroy the calibration manager
        </description>
      </request>

      <request name="cm_profile">
        <description summary="Request to calibrate/profile a given output">
          A program sends this request to a compositor to calibrate/profile a
          given output, it will use the provided surface to display the
          profile/calibration data and potentially user assistance information.

          A compositor can deny this request (for example when the output is in
          use by another full screen application or when in an HDR state that
          can't be calibrated/profiled), in this case it should give an error as
           defined in the exception enum and the first event of the calibration
           object must be a cancled event.
        </description>
        <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zwp_output_cal_v1" />
        <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface" />
        <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output" />
      </request>

      <enum name="exceptions">
        <entry name="not_supported" value="0" summary="Output doesn't suport calibration/profiling" />
        <entry name="not_saved" value="1" summary="Afer calibration/profiling no profile or video card lut was saved" />
        <entry name="user_cancled" value="3" summary="User cancled calibration"/>
        <entry name="output_in_use" value="4" summary="Output in use by other callibration and/or fullscreen application" />
      </enum>

      <event name="exception">
          <description summary="A runtime error happened see exceptions enum for more info"/>
          <arg name="error" type="uint" enum="exceptions" />
          <arg name="reason" type="string" summary="Short human readable description of error" />
      </event>

  </interface>

  <interface name="zwp_output_cal_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="Main calibration profiling interface">
      This is the interface that the calibrator/profiler will use to actually
      calibrate/profile a screen. The buffer of the attached surface will be
      displayed above everything else in full screen and the compositor should
      disable any DPMS/screensaver. Locking is still allowed so long as the Lock
      screen is not displayed on top of the calibration surface.

      The surface will be displayed as if it was in the display color space. So
      the compositor CMM should at most do an identy transform or blit the buffer
      as directly to the screen as possible (depending on how the compositor
      normally operates with surfaces in the display color space)

      The compositor is allowed to stop the process at any time by sending a
      cancled event. In this case the surface will be unmapped any calibration
      done will be undone and no further events will be sent nor any request
      honered. The application should destroy this interface in that case.
    </description>

    <enum name="bitdepth">
      <entry name="NA" value="0" summary="Not used (only valid for Gamma_in/out)" />
      <entry name="8bit" value="1" summary="8 Bit display" />
      <entry name="10bit" value="2" summary="10 Bit display" />
      <entry name="12bit" value="3" summary="12 Bit display" />
      <entry name="14bit" value="4" summary="14 Bit display" />
    </enum>

    <event name="display_config">
      <description summary="Event send to inform application of display depth">
        This event will be fired on creation of an wp_output_cal object;
        providing the calibration program the nescary information for
        calibrating/profiling the screen.

        NOTE: If the compositor is using a shader for the LUT/gamma table it is
        free to set anything for the Gamma_in/out. If using the video card LUT
        it should provide the size of that LUT.

        In some cases LUT/gamma tables are not provided (e.g. some display HW
        has only 1 shared over all displays so only the main display can be
        calibrated)

        The client must obey the size exactly on the next commit with a wl_buffer.
      </description>
      <arg name="depth" type="uint" enum="bitdepth" summary="Current display bit depth" />
      <arg name="Gamma_in" type="uint" enum="bitdepth" summary="Input size of LUT/Gamma table" />
      <arg name="Gamma_out" type="uint" enum="bitdepth" summary="Output size of LUT/Gamma table" />
      <arg name="width" type="uint" summary="widht of output in pixels" />
      <arg name="height" type="uint" summary="height of output in pixels" />
    </event>

    <event name="cancled">
      <description summary="Event sent in case calibration is cancled/aborted">
        This events denotes that the calibration is aborted/cancled or (in the
        case this is the first event) the calibration can't start.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="id_lut">
      <description summary="Request to create an identy LUT of right size for this output"/>
      <arg name="lut" type="new_id" interface="zwp_cm_lut" summary="object holding the id LUT" />
    </request>


    <reqest name="get_lut">
      <description summary="Get the current LUT">
        With this request a program can gets a copy of the current loaded LUT
      </description>
      <arg name="lut" type="new_id" interface="zwp_cm_lut" summary="Object describing a LUT"/>
    </request>

    <request name="load_lut">
      <description summary="Request to load a new LUT">
        To setup a new LUT, this is traditionally loaded in either the Video
        card LUT/Gamma table. But a compositor is free to use a shader instead.

        This request will only be honered if the Gamma_in/out are actually
        provided.
      </description>
      <arg name="lut" type="object" interface="zwp_cm_lut" summary="Object providing a LUT" />
      <arg name="callback" type="new_id" interface="wl_callback" summary="callback that will fire when callibration curve is loaded" />
    </request>

    <request name="load_profile">
      <description summary="Load a given profile including VCGT">
        USed to load a given ICC profile a compositor should also apply the VCGT
        if provided, traditionally this is done wiht the video card LUT/Gamma
        table but a compositor is free to do it in a shader so long as it is
        done after any of the CMM transforms (as the last step before pushing
        to the screen).

        If this interface is destroyed without saving compositor should
        restore previous settings
      </description>
      <arg name="profile" type="fd" summary="file descriptor to ICC profile"/>
      <arg name="callback" type="new_id" summary="callback that will fire when profile is loaded" />
    </request>

    <request name="save" type="destructor">
      <decsription summary="Last profile loaded should be saved">
        Send this to save the last profile loaded, compositor is allowed to
        check this profile and deny the reqest (see error enum in manager interface).
        irregardless of if profile gets saved or not this will destroy this interface.
        If not saved compositor should restore previous settings.
      </description>
    </reqest>

    <request name="desstroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="Destroy object without saving" />
    </request>

  </interface>

  <interface name="zwp_cm_lut" version="1">
    <description summary="Object for holding calibration LUT data">
      The compositor will create an ammount of shared memory that will hold the
      LUT data. It will be in a format of an array of unsigned 16 bit integers
      (little endian), with a lenght of 3x the LUT input size. The red, green and
      blue information will be stored interlaced (so R1,G1,B1,R2,G2,B2,etc).

      The 16bit integers will be scaled to the output LUT size, effectively making
      the output size determine the step size of the 16bit integers.

      In case there is no LUT the no_LUT event will be provided.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="Destroy the LUT">
        Destroy the LUT and any associated data
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="no_LUT" />

    <event name="LUT_data">
      <description summary="fd to shared memory">
        This event will be fired on creating a zwp_cm_lute and will provide a
        file descriptor the the shared memory provided for storing a LUT
      </description>
      <arg name="shm" type="fd" />
    </event>

    <request name="set_new_LUT">
      <description summary="set a new LUT">
        Provide a new LUT in described format
      </description>
      <arg name="shm" type="fd" />
    </request>

  </interface>

</protocol>
